<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>./valinsky.sh | ./valinsky.sh</title>
        <link>https://valinsky.me/</link>
        <description>./valinsky.sh | ./valinsky.sh</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 10:49:18 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://valinsky.me/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
                <title>Posts</title>
                <link>https://valinsky.me/posts/</link>
                <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 10:49:18 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://valinsky.me/posts/</guid>
                <description></description>
            </item><item>
                <title>Privacy Statement</title>
                <link>https://valinsky.me/privacy-statement/</link>
                <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 19:14:55 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://valinsky.me/privacy-statement/</guid>
                <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;github&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this website is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/valinsky/valinsky.github.io&#34;&gt;publicly available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website is hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/github/site-policy/github-privacy-statement#github-pages&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you create a GitHub Pages website, it is your responsibility to post a privacy statement that accurately describes how you
collect, use, and share personal information and other visitor information, and how you comply with applicable data privacy
laws, rules, and regulations. Please note that GitHub may collect Technical Information from visitors to your GitHub Pages
website, including logs of visitor IP addresses, to maintain the security and integrity of the website and service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analytics&#34;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using Google Analytics as a third party tracking service. We do not use it to track you individually or collect personal information about you. Google Analytics is used to collect information about website performance and how users of this website interact with it. This helps us understand user interests better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only collect the minimum amount of personal information required to understand the purpose of your interactions with this website. This information, as far as we are aware, will not be sold to third parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Analytics gathers certain simple, non-personally identifying information over time, such as your IP address, browser type, internet service provider, referring and exit pages, time stamp, and similar data about your use of this website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can opt out of Google Analytics tracking by using a script blocking browser extension or add-on and simply disabling the Google Analytics script. Google also provides a browser &lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout&#34;&gt;add-on to block GA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://policies.google.com/technologies/partner-sites&#34;&gt;Googles Privacy Policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            </item><item>
                <title>About</title>
                <link>https://valinsky.me/about/</link>
                <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 20:35:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://valinsky.me/about/</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, my name is Vali and I love the [free, open, uncensored, secure and E2EE] internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            </item></channel>
</rss>
