<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Valinsky</title>
    <link>https://valinsky.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Valinsky</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 15:15:12 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://valinsky.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CalyxOS</title>
      <link>https://valinsky.me/posts/calyxos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 15:15:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://valinsky.me/posts/calyxos/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been using CalyxOS for about a month on a Pixel 4a and I love it. It feels so liberating to use a mobile FOSS OS without all the privacy intruding Google spyware.
Apps While transitioning to CalyxOS I realized I was using many apps that I didn&amp;rsquo;t really need. This was the perfect time get rid of them. The less apps you have on your phone the better.
The apps that I ended up still using work well on CalyxOS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Built a Twitter Bot</title>
      <link>https://valinsky.me/posts/i-built-a-twitter-bot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 15:15:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://valinsky.me/posts/i-built-a-twitter-bot/</guid>
      <description>On the 11th of May, 2020, at block height 630.000, the 3rd Bitcoin halving event happened.
For us Bitcoin nerds this was a huge event, not only because it happens every 4 years or because of its economic implications, but also because it shows the beautiful system that Bitcoin has in place, a system that has been working flawlessly since 2009.
To commemorate this event, I thought about creating a Twitter bot that keeps track of how many blocks are left until the next halving.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Magic of Quake 3&#39;s Fast Inverse Square Root Explained</title>
      <link>https://valinsky.me/posts/quake3-fast-inverse-square-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 17:24:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://valinsky.me/posts/quake3-fast-inverse-square-root/</guid>
      <description>This is one of those magical unicorn algorithms.
I was always intrigued by this small piece of code, because it&amp;rsquo;s such a unique and elegant solution to a common problem, and it&amp;rsquo;s part of a game I played a lot as a kid. I did not understand it then, but I do now.
This algorithm estimates the inverse square root, \( 1 / \sqrt{number} \), of a positive 32 bit floating point number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Statement</title>
      <link>https://valinsky.me/privacy-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 19:14:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://valinsky.me/privacy-statement/</guid>
      <description>GitHub The code for this website is publicly available on GitHub.
The website is hosted on GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages privacy policy
 If you create a GitHub Pages website, it is your responsibility to post a privacy statement that accurately describes how you collect, use, and share personal information and other visitor information, and how you comply with applicable data privacy laws, rules, and regulations. Please note that GitHub may collect Technical Information from visitors to your GitHub Pages website, including logs of visitor IP addresses, to maintain the security and integrity of the website and service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to configure your Github Pages website with your custom Godaddy domain</title>
      <link>https://valinsky.me/posts/github-pages-with-custom-godaddy-domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 10:54:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://valinsky.me/posts/github-pages-with-custom-godaddy-domain/</guid>
      <description>You can use your own custom domain with GitHub Pages, instead of GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io domain. This GitHub Pages post covers the domain configuration steps.
If you bought the domain on GoDaddy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you the exact GoDaddy DNS configuration you need.
Go to your godaddy.com domain, and find the Manage DNS option.
GoDaddy Manage DNS  Add these settings.
GoDaddy DNS configuration  My website is hosted on GitHub under the valinsky.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
