<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vali Voicu</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vali Voicu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:04:35 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Build 2020</title>
      <link>/posts/privacy-build-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:04:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/privacy-build-2020/</guid>
      <description>Privacy was a hot topic in the last decade. And for good reason. A lot of companies are thriving based on the business model of gathering as much data as they can from their customers and using that data to gain influence and to generate profit.
Companies started employing intelligent and invasive tracking methods to gather user data and use intelligent word play to hide the underlying techniques used. A lot of people have no idea how their data is being used, or that they themselves have become a product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stop Over Planning</title>
      <link>/posts/stop-over-planning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 21:40:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/stop-over-planning/</guid>
      <description>Planning is an essential aspect of a healthy lifestyle. We try to systematically structure our daily activities in order to take full advantage of our time.
For me it wasn&amp;rsquo;t that simple. Planning often turned out to be a productivity killer and a cause for stress. I realized that was because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how my mind worked and I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to adapt to it.
You can&amp;rsquo;t plan inspiration We&amp;rsquo;re all living that busy 21st century life, trying to find a balance between family, partners, work, gym, nutrition, finances, school, friends, hobbies, hustling, side projects, lazyness, vacations, unforseen events, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Magic of Quake 3&#39;s Fast Inverse Square Root Explained</title>
      <link>/posts/quake3-fast-inverse-square-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 17:24:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/quake3-fast-inverse-square-root/</guid>
      <description>This is one of those magical unicorn algorithms.
I was always intrigued by this small piece of code, because it&amp;rsquo;s such a unique and elegant solution to a common problem, and it&amp;rsquo;s part of a game I played a lot as a kid. I did not understand it then, but I do now.
This algorithm estimates the inverse square root, \( 1 / \sqrt{number} \), of a positive 32 bit floating point number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Statement</title>
      <link>/privacy-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 19:14:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy-statement/</guid>
      <description>GitHub The code for this website is publicly available on GitHub.
The website is hosted on GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages privacy policy
 If you create a GitHub Pages website, it is your responsibility to post a privacy statement that accurately describes how you collect, use, and share personal information and other visitor information, and how you comply with applicable data privacy laws, rules, and regulations. Please note that GitHub may collect Technical Information from visitors to your GitHub Pages website, including logs of visitor IP addresses, to maintain the security and integrity of the website and service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to configure your Github Pages website with your custom Godaddy domain</title>
      <link>/posts/github-pages-with-custom-godaddy-domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 10:54:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/github-pages-with-custom-godaddy-domain/</guid>
      <description>You can use your own custom domain with GitHub Pages, instead of GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io domain. This GitHub Pages post covers the domain configuration steps.
If you bought the domain on GoDaddy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you the exact GoDaddy DNS configuration you need.
Go to your godaddy.com domain, and find the Manage DNS option.
GoDaddy Manage DNS  Add these settings.
GoDaddy DNS configuration  My website is hosted on GitHub under the valinsky.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 20:35:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi, my name is Vali and I love the [free, open, uncensored, secure and E2EE] internet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>