<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>privacy on Vali Voicu</title>
    <link>/tags/privacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in privacy on Vali Voicu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:04:35 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Build 2020</title>
      <link>/posts/privacy-build-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:04:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/privacy-build-2020/</guid>
      <description>Privacy was a hot topic in the last decade. And for good reason. Corporations are thriving based on the business model of gathering as much data as they can from their customers and using that data to gain influence and to generate profit.
Companies started employing intelligent and invasive tracking methods to gather as much user data as possible while hiding the underlying techniques implemented through intelligent word play. A lot of people have no idea how their data is being used, or that they themselves have become a product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Statement</title>
      <link>/privacy-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 19:14:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy-statement/</guid>
      <description>GitHub The code for this website is publicly available on GitHub.
The website is hosted on GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages privacy policy
 If you create a GitHub Pages website, it is your responsibility to post a privacy statement that accurately describes how you collect, use, and share personal information and other visitor information, and how you comply with applicable data privacy laws, rules, and regulations. Please note that GitHub may collect Technical Information from visitors to your GitHub Pages website, including logs of visitor IP addresses, to maintain the security and integrity of the website and service.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>